So
this week before we dive into any actual
analysis of any real hands on data,
we're going to stop for a second and think
about what you need to think about before
you even analyze your data or even
send it off to the sequencer.
So this is all about the planning stage,
and we're going to be working through
a scenario together right now now,
which will hopefully happen to you
at some point during your career.
Perhaps you will get exciting news
from a colleague that a big grant has been
funded and they want to sequence ten
samples for project you
are working on together.
And with the expertise that you gained
during this class,
you agree to do the post-sequencing
bioinformatic analyses for them.
You are so excited to get started
with this project, but maybe we
should do some planning first.
So take 30 seconds right now to write down
a few topics you'll want to talk with your
colleague about before
any of the work begins.
I mean, you're gonna submit one
of those to me as a question right now.
Okay.
So we're back from you writing down a few
suggestions, and now take a second
to compare what you wrote down to some
of the considerations that I thought of,
which is by no means inclusive
of absolutely everything.
And I'm really excited to see the other
suggestions that you might have.
So what came to my mind right away? What
type of sequencing are we going to even
do? How much data are you going to need
to collect from each individual as far as
the actual material needed for sequencing,
how many replicates for your experiment?
Where will these samples actually be
sequenced at your University or your
collaborators University? Maybe that will
come down to the cost of doing
it at one of those places.
So there are a lot of decisions to be
made before any sequencing even begins.
Those are just a few of them.
So let's say that you've Dove
in and you've made a plan
and you have an experimental design
for maybe an RNA see experiment,
and you've chosen how you're going
to sequence and where you're going
to sequence your data and that you're
going to do the analysis, of course.
So now we're going to pause again and have
you take 30 seconds and again submit one
of these suggestions to me
and think of the types of data that you're
going to need for your analysis
that you're calling.
I need to record about these samples
before they are even
sent to the sequencer.
So what should they be keeping in mind if
they're the person who's actually getting
the material from the mice or
whatever you're experimenting upon?
Okay.
And again, let's compare.
You might have written down to some
examples that again,
I've had experience with in the past or
just now came to my mind again,
not totally inclusive.
And again, very excited to see if
you thought of something I didn't.
Of course, you're going to want to note,
however, you're keeping track of your
sample IDs for each of your samples,
whether they're individual tissue samples
or samples taken from different genotypes
of mice, whatever is relevant
for your study, basically.
So that would just be any characteristics
of the input material itself from DNA
concentration, the sequencing barcode.
You're giving it things that we'll be
talking about later in the course.
And then, as I mentioned, details
about the sample itself, of course.
So if it's relevant to you to know,
for example,
if the samples come from a male or female,
you're going to want
to collect that information.
If it's really important to know exactly
what tissue it came from for your
experiment, you will also record that.
So these details about the sample itself
are really dependent on exactly what
your variables of interest are.
But I would always recommend jotting down
probably more than you think,
especially if it's data you're not
going to be able to recreate later.
And we're going to talk about sort of
minimal reporting of different types
of this data for different types
of projects in the upcoming weeks as we
go through different types of fencing.
And so all of this type of data that's not
the actual sequencing data itself
or the experimental actual data
points is called metadata,
or, as we call it,
basically data about the data.
So here is data, the cat,
and perhaps some metadata that we
could collect about data.
The cat are things like, where was
this photo of this adorable cat taken?
And on what date?
Maybe that's going to help help us seek
out where this adorable cat is
living and pet it for ourselves.
And PS data would be
an excellent name for a cat.
So it's the data about the data,
and metadata is super important
for reasons that we will discover
together through this course.
I mean, ultimately, data is not
meaningful without metadata.
If you just have random sequencing
but didn't record which experimental
treatment it came from,
how you prepared the DNA for sequencing,
et cetera, et cetera.
You're not going to be able to sort
of link it back to the question
that you're trying to answer
by doing the sequencing.
So metadata
we can think of is the link between your
data and your original biological question
or the biological system at hand.
And in fact, organizations
have or in the process of establishing
standards for the type of metadata
that need to be included
with different types of sequencing.
So we'll talk about later in this course.
But when you submit your data as you
should to a public database,
when you're done with your project,
you really need to be careful about what
type of info they expect you
to submit with that data.
Okay.
So the moment has happened,
you are about to get your data back.
All that metadata has been collected,
but now there are a few
other things to consider.
So you know, you're about to get your
sequencing data in a couple of weeks.
It's in the sequencing queue.
Again, let's take a few seconds and think
of what things come to mind as
you prepare to receive the data.
That's going to save you big headaches
later as you are doing the analysis.
So
I'm just going to suggest a few whole
categories of things that I would
personally already be thinking about when
I know my data is on the way to coming
to me and for me to work on and again,
compare this to what you got.
I'm sure that some of these things are
things that you definitely thought of,
and perhaps some of them will be
new to you to be kind of exciting.
So
one big question is, where is
this data going to to get stored?
You'll see working through this course
that the sequencing files and all
of the intermediate files you generate
while working through a bioinformatics
pipeline are huge and quite plentiful.
So please note that all of the sizes
in this table are, in fact,
in gigabytes so they can fill up even big
terabyte size hard drives
in absolutely no time.
So might be by some
of those ahead of time.
Make sure your University's serve has
room for you, et cetera, et cetera.
On a similar note, where are
we going to analyze this data?
Many applications that are for processing
big data sets of sequencing data require
significant memory and or require parallel
processing processing,
meaning we need multiple processors
working in parallel to get the job done
in any sort of reasonable amount of time.
As we'll talk about,
this is something that's particularly
of a concern when doing things like
assembling whole Genome Gnomes.
So for the most part, we can't
run these directly on the laptop.
So you might want to start looking at,
for example, does your institution have
a computer cluster here at the NIH?
A huge part of my job is communicating
with a big super computer
that we call Bio Wolf.
During this course,
we're going to work on a public
server called the Galaxy Project.
You're going to be super
familiar with that.
And then there are things like
Amazon Web Services, which I'm sure
you've heard of that you can set up to.
Also do buyer Informatics on if your local
computing is not sufficient, but again,
totally planning this ahead of time.
Additionally, it's not enough to just be
like, okay, I'm going to use the server.
You also need to make sure of things like
is the software that I will need to get
my expected outputs from this data
even available on my University's server?
Do I need them to
install a bunch of things for me
been through that where software expected
was not actually there or not installed
properly or the most updated version.
You can also, for example,
decide what software to use by reading
studies that use similar data
to answer similar questions.
This is a huge part of preparing to do
an analysis, and we're going to read some
of those examples during this course
and also just starting to think about can
the software be chained together
in a pipeline
like this one that takes a certain input
data does a bunch of steps without you
needing to do any manual
input in the middle and then
produces an expected output.
And again, that's something
we will practice together.
So
one thing that's going to be key
to planning and analysis,
and that much detail is finding relevant
sequencing data that you can perhaps
practice on, or at least it'll provide
a backbone of building your own pipeline.
And perhaps I'll actually be good
to compare your results
to their findings to see if what you're
getting is reasonable
and sort of build upon that.
And luckily, it's pretty easy
to find relevant sequencing data.
So here is a paper
by some of my colleagues.
It is a very cool paper about single cell
sequencing in an invertebrate called
Hydra, and it's super cool study.
And so perhaps I want to compare it
to a project that I'm working on right now
that's working on single cell sequencing
and a relative of this organism.
So very cool.
But where can I find the raw data to
compare to my own organism of interest?
Luckily, most papers have what's called
a data statement in the side of them,
as required by different federal
and otherwise granting agencies.
Many things actually require this.
Many publications actually
require this as well.
And so you can scroll down to this.
This is often near the
acknowledgement section and find some
little, very helpful numbers here.
And we're going to focus on this bio
project number I put in a box right here.
So we're going to do this in practice
in one of the next tutorials.
But just as an example, you can search
this number on the NCBI website,
and it'll take you to this whole page
about this project,
and we can retrieve in absolutely tons
of information and the structure of one
of these bio projects as we'll go
into more depth about essentially,
it looks like this.
So we have our overarching project that
has an ID number that looks like this.
It contains information about individual
samples that are within this study.
So perhaps these are two different
whole samples of that Hydro organism.
And then perhaps those biosamples,
one of them was used to generate
some short sequencing reads.
And perhaps those are the ones we're
interested in for our single
cell sequencing analysis.
And perhaps another sample was used
to generate a genome sequence that we can
use in conjunction with the short read
data of whatever type that it is.
Of course, project structures can be a bit
more complicated, because if you probably
imagine,
you can have sub projects where maybe
you're very focused on the transcriptome
of certain samples for a while.
And also, of course,
you might imagine that individual
samples are the same genotype.
You probably want to get a transcriptome
in a genome from the same organism to make
down Stanly is as easy as possible.
So in reality,
more than an organized hierarchy,
sometimes it looks kind of like a web,
but we're going to practice navigating
this web together in this week and pretty
much in every future week as a way
of getting publicly available data
that we're going to use
throughout this course.
What you'll find if you click through
enough links as we will do that we're
in the NCBI short Read Archive, or SRA,
and what this is the raw data
associated sequencing projects.
So, for example, for this one,
it'll get you to a list of a bunch
of different luminous sequence sing runs
of different tissue types from that same
Hydra sequencing project.
And again, we're going to get plenty
of practice finding and downloading data
from the SRA during this course as early
as pretty much the first tutorial here.
So to summarize,
there is plenty to consider before
the analysis, even beacons so, of course,
experimental design and other
pre sequencing concerns.
What metadata are we gonna to make sure
to get before it goes to the sequencer?
Where to store the data,
where to analyze the data?
What software do we need? And of course,
is there similar data out there
to practice on and compare our results to
thanks so much for listening and good
luck with this week's projects.