So last week you gained experience with
two steps that are gonna be in common
with pretty much every sequencing analysis
we do in this course. Um, so namely,
um, that is getting sequencing
reads from a source,
so publicly available databases in
our case, um, and then performing, um,
quality troll on them. Um,
and so this week we are gonna
build on that knowledge, um,
to see how to use a
polished set of reads, um,
such as the ones we
generated last week, um,
to answer an actual biological
question this time. Um,
and the first thing we're gonna
learn about and do this week, um,
is all about the process of
mapping, read to a reference genome,
a process that we will also be doing
repeatedly throughout the course. Um,
and this will also entail us
learning about a new file format, um,
that holds this mapping and
alignment information. Then,
uh,
we're gonna explore one of
the many possible downstream
applications of quality,
the control and mapping that is
variant calling or finding out,
um, places where your sample
differs from that reference genome.
You did the alignment too. Um, and again,
this process is called variant calling
and you can use it for a number of very
interesting, important
applications, um, in particular, uh,
you will be using it to look at, um,
some samples of SARS
Cove, two genomes, um,
from around the Boston
area and beyond, um,
and check whether or not they have
diagnostic mutations associated with the
Delta variant. Um, so very hands on
and very, um, sort of, of the moment,
highly relevant dataset, um,
and to support you towards that
independent analysis of the SARS Cove,
two genomes and their variants, um,
there will be several
lectures and tutorials, um,
and then our weekly assignments, um,
are some of those knowledge check
quizzes to help you along the way, um,
a weekly discussion, um,
about variant calling, um,
and finally a major assignment and it's
accompanying a peer reviewed writing
assignment, um, just like
last week and as always, um,
my office hours are open as is the
weekly help discussion board. Uh,
good luck this week, everyone.